He says מרי שמה לאו. marei shemeh lav. No, because it’s you’re
saying that it’s a new name but really it isn’t, it’s still
the same name. דתניא De'tanya צדדי הבית tziddei habayit אלו המלטטין elu
hameltatin והעובים veha'uvim אלו המרשין. elu hamarshin. Anyways, in יחזקאל Yechezkel talking
about the third בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and he’s talking about building
it and he’s talking about עובים uvim like groups and whatever it
is, but the question, the explanation is these are מרשין. marshin. These
are these beams. So meaning that even though it’s the roof it’s
still called beams. So the point is that the beam is still
considered a beam even if I put it in my roof. It’s
not really a שינוי השם. shinnuy hashem. I guess there’s some things
that’s really a שינוי השם shinnuy hashem and some things that’s not
so much a שינוי השם. shinnuy hashem. So this
2x4 you look at it and you say oh there’s a 2x4
over there. You don’t necessarily say oh it’s a roof, right?
Whereas you would say this is a mat as opposed to saying
this is just a piece of leather. So you can’t question me
on the beam. The beam really hasn’t changed its name.
So no question on me. רבי זירא אמר. Rebbi Zeira amar. רבי
זירא Rebbi Zeira gives a different answer. שינוי החוזר לברייתו בשינוי השם
לא הוי שינוי. Shinnuy hachozer livriyato beshinnuy hashem lo havei shinnuy. So
he’s saying oh it depends if you can sort of if it
can be reversed, if it’s a reversible שינוי. shinnuy. So even if
it’s a שינוי השם shinnuy hashem
if it can be reversed then
it’s
not really enough of a שינוי. shinnuy. So basically in the case
of a beam let’s say
the reason why the guy doesn’t get it בשינוי השם beshinnuy hashem
is not because so much of שינוי השם shinnuy hashem but let’s
say let’s say my house sort of fell down, right? That 2x4
would just be the same 2x4 as before. Again I didn’t dye
it, I didn’t sculpt it, there’s no molding on it, there’s no
nothing. If I did some of that that’d be different. All I
did was just sort of use it as one of many beams
and it’s there. I didn’t cut it, I didn’t trim it, didn’t
anything.
So since it can be reversed that’s why he’s not קונה koneh
right because I mean that’s the whole point, right? That’s the proof
for רבי יוסף. Rebbi Yosef. רבי יוסף Rebbi Yosef can say I
mean he still agrees with רבי יוסף Rebbi Yosef but from a
different answer
that reversible שינוי השם shinnuy hashem is not
קונה. koneh. That’s so רבי יוסף Rebbi Yosef would be right. And
so the only reason is תקנת השבים. takanat hashavim. So why doesn’t
he have to return it? He right in a normal case he
would have to return
it but we’re not going to force him to tear down the
house to give it back. That’s why we say תקנת השבים. takanat
hashavim. And otherwise you would have to give it back. Again why
would he have to give it back? Because it’s a reversible שינוי
shinnuy as opposed to like let’s say I the leather that I
made into shoes, right? Now it’s a pair of shoes and I’m
walking around he’s like give me back my leather. Like no that’s
a שינוי מעשה shinnuy ma'aseh and a שינוי השם. shinnuy hashem. Right
now it’s shoes. So let’s say the case of the tray he
doesn’t have to give like if you whatever it
is you
warped it a little, you stitched it,
whatever the same idea
that if it’s a שינוי מעשה shinnuy ma'aseh it wouldn’t get back
but שינוי השם shinnuy hashem if it’s just a שינוי השם shinnuy
hashem that even if you build it to something it can be
reversed and then that’s not a שינוי shinnuy enough. So that answers
the wood case.
So okay basically his point is that a שינוי החוזר לברייתו בשינוי
השם shinnuy hachozer livriyato beshinnuy hashem is not really a שינוי. shinnuy.
So the גמרא Gemara says is that really true? ושינוי השם שאינו
חוזר
לברייתו מי הוי שינוי?
Veshinnuy hashem she'eino chozer
livriyato mi havei shinnuy? If it so basically if it can be
reversed it is a שינוי shinnuy I mean if it sorry if
it can be reversed then it’s not a שינוי shinnuy but if
it can’t be reversed then it isn’t. So is that really true?
והרי צינורא Vaharei tzinnora a pipe מעיקרא חתיתא והשתא צינורא. me'ikara chatita
vehashta tzinnora.
So let's say you make a wood pipe. So you got a
block of wood so you hollow it out and you put it
and attach it to the pipe so now it's a pipe. Okay.
ותניא Vetanya צינור שחקקו ולבסוף קבעו פוסל את המקווה. tzinnor shechakako ulevasof
kava'o poseil et hamikvah. קבעו ולבסוף חקקו אינו פוסל את המקווה. Kava'o
ulevasof chakako eino poseil et hamikvah. So we all know that you
can't have מים שאובים mayim she'uvim drawn water in a מקווה. mikvah.
So let's say I have a pipe right and this would
forget the exact case as to how this is done. So let's
say I made a pipe and then I took this piece of
wood I hollowed it out I attached it to whatever it is
stuck it to the ground so that the rain
water will like be channeled
through wherever it is go through this pipe and go into my
pit that I dug as a מקווה mikvah right? So if I
did all that I took a wood I hollowed it out I
attached it to whatever and then attached it to the other pipe
and now this is now attached to the ground right? So it'll
fill up the ground the pit whatever.
So if I do all that then it is פוסל את המקווה.
poseil et hamikvah. But let's say I stuck it into the ground
as a piece of wood then I hollowed it out and guess
what now it's a pipe right? That's not considered a problem. That
would not be פוסל את המקווה. poseil et hamikvah. ואי אמרת
שינוי
השם מילתא היא. Ve'ee amrat shinnuy hashem milta hi. saying that שינוי
שם shinoi shem is is you know is good אפילו afilu קבעו
ko-avo so חקקו chakako נמי nami לפסול. lifsol.
So why would it be in that second case if I attached
it to the ground and I hollowed it out that
it's
good? Why? It should be פסול pasul
because you know you're saying that it's a שינוי שם shinoi shem
and it's a שינוי שם shinoi shem and it's not reversible.
So if it's a שינוי שם shinoi shem and not reversible you're
saying that's you know a real שינוי, shinoi, right? So if it's
a real שינוי shinoi then it should פסול pasul המקוה ha-mikvah because
you know just like in the second case. What's the difference? Who
cares if you attached it to the ground and hollowed it out?
It's a שינוי. shinoi. I did a שינוי. shinoi. Why is that
not a problem of מים שאובים? mayim shu-uvim? So he says שאני
התם דדרבנן
היא.
shani hasam
de-rabbanan hi.
So you know so drawn waters is a rabbinic problem. So אי
הכי אפילו רישא נמי. ei hachi afilu reisha nami. So okay so
then so if it's only a rabbinic problem then why are you
splitting your rulings? Right? In one case you're saying it's a problem,
in one case you're saying it isn't. If it's a problem it
should be a problem in all cases, right? If it's not a
problem it should not be a problem in the other cases, right?
So meaning in the you know so if you're saying it's all
דרבנן de-rabbanan it shouldn't be a problem even in the case where
I where you know it was a pipe to begin where I
you know even before where I didn't attach to the ground where
I just you know hollowed it out and then attached then attached
it. Why should that be a problem? You're saying it's a problem.
Why should why should it be a problem? You're saying that the
you know this whole rabbinic you know thing we're not going to
be so strict about it. So why are we strict about it
in the first case? Either be either be consistent.
Strict you know it's either good or bad in all cases.
So he says no.
He says התם איכא תורת כלי עליה בתלוש הכא ליכא תורת כלי
עליה בתלוש. hatam ika toras kli aleia b'talush hacha leika toras kli
aleia b'talush. No I mean the difference is you know look at
it when it was you know when at the state where you're
attaching it. In the in the first case you made into a
כלי, kli, right? As I said you you had the wood, you
hollowed it out, before it was a piece of wood, now it's
a pipe. But in the second case you know in the second
case it wasn't a it was just a piece of wood. It
was a block of wood which I stuck into the ground, just
a block of wood on the ground. Then I hollowed it out.
So the difference is you know
we're saying yeah you know it was דרבנן de-rabbanan but okay we're
not going to take this דרבנן de-rabbanan so far like we're not
going to say that it's always דרבנן de-rabbanan we're going to be
lenient in all cases. Let's see whether there's a כלי kli or
not you know in its present state when you did all this.
If it was a כלי, kli, you know, then we're going to
say it's a problem and if it wasn't a כלי kli we're
going to say that it's not.
So so again so in the first case where I took the
piece of wood I hollowed it out and I attached it now
you know before I attached it was already a כלי. kli. So
that's why it's a problem. In the second case where it was
a block of wood and I stuck it into the ground and
then I hollowed it out you know when when I stuck it
into the ground it was not a כלי. kli. So that's why
it's not a problem.
So anyway what we're still what we're still maintaining is is that
the
you know that we can defend רב יוסף Rav Yosef who says
ייאוש ye-ush is not קונה koneh because רב יוסף Rav Yosef talked
about like just a case where there was ייאוש ye-ush and nothing
else. You know we can debate you know שינוי השם shinoi hashem
and שינוי מעשה shinoi ma'aseh you know what how far do you
take it but you know but רב יוסף Rav Yosef can can
get out of it and say all these questions you're you're asking
me from it wasn't just a straight ייאוש ye-ush case there was
some sort of שינוי. shinoi. Again whether you know does it need
to be reversible does it not need to be reversible you know
all these are details we can work out he's saying.
But you know the core of my position of straight ייאוש ye-ush
has not been challenged yet that it has no effect because all
your all your challenges are specific. Okay? So again so we challenged
רבא Rava who managed to get out of it with the חמץ
בפסח chametz b'Pesach case and then the קרבן korban case you know
again רבא's Rava the one that says ייאוש ye-ush does have an
effect and we've seen that those cases you know doesn't but then
we answered that those are specific cases. And we asked questions on
רב יוסף Rav Yosef who holds it doesn't have an effect with
cases it seems that it does have an effect but he answered
all those by saying that it wasn't just a straight ייאוש ye-ush
case it was a ייאוש ye-ush and a שינוי, shinoi, שינוי השם,
shinoi hashem, שינוי מעשה, shinoi ma'aseh, whichever. מתיבי גנב וגזלן ואנס הקדישו
הקדש ותרומתו תרומה ומעשרותיו מעשר. meisivei ganav v'gazlan v'anas hikdisho hekdesh v'terumaso
terumah u-ma'aserosav ma'aser. So
okay so let's say there's no שינוי shinoi at all it would
seem like I stole something and you know I stole your I
stole your קרבן korban and I הקדיש-ed hikdish it, right?
Or I stole your you know your wheat and and I and
you know now took תרומה terumah
or מעשר ma'aser you know or טבל tevel whatever you know your
whatever it was and I and I took תרומה, terumah, מעשר, ma'aser,
made it a קרבן. korban. It works! Right? Why would it work?
So the answer is no התם איכא שינוי השם דמעיקרא טבלא והשתא
תרומה הקדש מעיקרא חולין והשתא הקדש. hatam ika shinoi hashem de-me-ikara tavla
ve-hashta terumah hekdesh me-ikara chulin ve-hashta hekdesh.
Right? So again
רב יוסף Rav Yosef this is the question on רב יוסף, Rav
Yosef, right? Because if ייאוש ye-ush is not קונה koneh then why
would a גנב ganav be able to do anything? He again he
didn't do any what change did he do? The answer is he
did do a שינוי. shinoi. He did a שינוי השם. shinoi hashem.
When I took your wheat yes the same wheat now before but
it's not the same wheat now as before physically. same wheat, but
now it's called something else. You took תרומה, terumah, you're not going
to- you're not going to look at it, you're not going to
look at it the same way. תרומה Terumah has its own set
of laws. You- you know, it's now תרומה terumah now, before it
was just a, you know, a regular sheep now. It's not a
sheep anymore, it's a קרבן. korban. So there's a שינוי השם. shinuy
hashem. You can't ask me, Rav Yosef would say, on this kind
of a case where there's a שינוי, shinuy, my position is that
if there's no שינוי shinuy then the יאוש yeush wouldn't have any,
any effect. So meaning like, you know, let's say the גנב ganav
didn't do anything. He would have to give it back, right? So
like he's not- he wouldn't be קונה. koneh. Yeah. Yes.
If, if you have stolen, for example, species, then it's not valid
for a מצוה.
mitzvah. Right, that's something, yeah.
So isn't this using something stolen for a מצוה?
mitzvah? Right, I know that. I have that same, I have that
same question. But I think, but I think that, but I think
that- I don't know. I don't know how you answer that. Like,
you know, I would think that and first we're going to see
something, you know, the גמרא Gemara is going to get back to
this. But, but yeah, I mean, that is a good question. אמר
רב חסדא אמר יונתן. Amar Rav Chisda amar Yonatan. So now we're
going to have two teachings in the name of יונתן Yonatan which
should be exact opposite of one from the other. מנין לשינוי שהוא
קונה? Menayin leshinuy shehu koneh? So you know, the- how do we
know the שינוי shinuy works? שנאמר והשיב את
הגזלה אשר גזל.
She-ne'emar vehishiv et hagezeilah asher
gazal. That's- so why do you need to say that? Of course
you're going to bring back something- the stolen object that you stole.
You're not bringing back a stolen object that you didn't steal, right?
So what do you need to say אשר גזל asher gazal for?
מה תלמוד לומר אשר גזל? Mah talmud lomar asher gazal? So what
it comes to teach you: אם כעין שגזל יחזיר ואם לאו דמים
בעלמא בעי
שלומי.
im ke-ein shegazal yachazir ve-im lav damim be-alma
ba'ei shilumei. So if it's still in the same state, then I
give back the object, but if not, then I have to pay
him for it. So that's what it's coming- it's coming to teach
you. So I have to- I have to- you have to make
restitution either through דמים damim or through the object, you know, depending
on whether it is in the same state, it would be one
or the other. So you teach- so now you're saying that אשר
גזל asher gazal means to make this nuance? But no, אשר גזל
asher gazal is coming to teach something else. איבעי ליה למעוטי גזל
אביו שאינו מוסיף חומש על גזל אביו. Iba'ei lei lema'utei gezel aviv
she-eino mosif chomesh al gezel aviv. So like let's say, you know,
someone stole something from his father and then the father died, now
the son wants to bring back the גזילה, gezeilah, but the- you
know, but the point is that if you have stolen something and
admit to it, right, and not witnesses, not תנא גנבא tanna ganava
or not עדים, edim, but you just admit it on your own,
you have to pay the קרן והחומש, keren vehachomesh, right? So that's
if you do it. But let's say- let's say you're no longer
around and your children are doing it for you, they just give
back the object, they don't have to pay the חומש. chomesh. They're
admitting it, but it's not the same person that's admitting it. So
you don't say that the- that the, you know, the heirs are
like the person himself and have to pay the חומש. chomesh. No,
we don't say that. And we learn all that from אשר גזל.
asher gazal.
So no, but you can still learn both sets of laws, that-
to get you out of a חומש chomesh and that you give
back the object versus דמים damim depending on what kind of state
the object is in, because if you just want to learn one
of them, this law of not paying a חומש, chomesh, אי הכי
נכתוב רחמנא והשיב את הגזילה אשר גזל. im hachi niktov Rachamana vehishiv
et hagezeilah asher gazal. למה לי למכתב והשיב את הגזילה אשר גזל
Lama li limichtav vehishiv et hagezeilah asher gazal versus גזילה? gezeilah? שמע
מינה תרתי. Shma mina tarti. Okay, I can learn both. So fine.
So- so his point is that שינוי shinuy is קונה, koneh, right?
That's why he used to learn אשר גזל. asher gazal. If it's
like the same state, then- then you have to give it back,
if not, then you don't, because שינוי shinuy would be קונה. koneh.
איכא דאמרי אמר רב חסדא אמר יונתן Ika d'amri amar Rav Chisda
amar Yonatan the opposite. מנין לשינוי שאינו קונה? Menayin leshinuy she-eino koneh?
It's not קונה. koneh. שנאמר She-ne'emar from the same פסוק, pasuk, והשיב
את הגזילה. vehishiv et hagezeilah. You have to bring back the גזילה
gezeilah בכל מקום. bechol makom. I don't care if it's the same
way or not, same state. So שינוי shinuy isn't קונה, koneh, you
still give that back. What do you mean? והא כתיב אשר גזל?
Veha ketiv asher gazal? What about the אשר גזל? asher gazal? No,
ההוא מיבעי ליה על גזילו שלו הוא שמוסיף חומש ואינו מוסיף חומש
על גזל אביו. hahu miba'ei lei al gezeilo shelo hu shemosif chomesh
ve-eino mosif chomesh al gezel aviv. So אשר גזל asher gazal is
not coming to teach you that- that only if it's אשר גזל,
asher gazal, if it's the same state. That's coming to teach the
law of- that you don't pay חומש chomesh for your father. So
basically we- you know, we haven't answered our מחלוקת machloket whether there's
like Rav Yosef and- and this is very well articulated in this
last point even that- that there's a- that even a שינוי, shinuy,
you know, forget about just straight יאוש, yeush, even a שינוי shinuy
may- you- you may have to give back depending, you know. This-
this teaching said both ways: you do or you don't. So you
know, and it's from the same פסוק pasuk even. So we haven't
answered our debate. So we're continuing. אמר עולא, Amar Ulla, מנין ליאוש
שאינו קונה? Menayin l'yeush she-eino koneh? So how do we know that
יאוש yeush does not work, which would be like Rav Yosef's position?
That it says, שנאמר והבאתם גזול ואת הפיסח ואת החולה, she-ne'emar vahasatem
gazul ve'et hepise'ach ve'et hacholeh, right?
Which is what you were saying. That you're, you know, you're bringing
a stolen קרבן korban to השם Hashem or a sick קרבן. korban.
You know, would God want it? No, He wouldn't want it. So
meaning it's not good.
But here you're learning גזול דומיא דפיסח. gazul dumya de-pise'ach. מה פיסח
לית ליה תקנתא? Mah pise'ach leit lei takanta? As long as this
thing is- is lame, right? You- you know, you can't bring a
lame קרבן. korban. That's the end of it. Like, you know, let's
say it's missing a leg, you can't like glue a leg back.
But you know, even the point is, you know, it will get
better, like, you know, as long as it's in its state of
being lame, that's not an acceptable קרבן. korban. מה
פיסח לית ליה תקנתא כלל אף גזול לית ליה תקנתא.
Mah pise'ach leit lei takanta klal
af gazul leit lei takanta. Even a stolen object does not have
a תקנה. takana. ולא שנא לפני יאוש ולא שנא לאחר יאוש. Velo
shna lifnei yeush velo shna le-achar yeush. You cannot bring it. Doesn't
make a difference, אה יאוש ah yeush or not. So then the
question would be, you know, what do you do about that other
case before that.
So about, you know, that the הקדש *hekdesh* הקדש *hekdesh*. So, you
know, you might, we'll, we'll get to it, we'll just bear with
me, we're going to address that right now. So רבא אמר מהכא
קרבנו ולא גזול *Rava amar mehacha korbano velo gozul*, right? You can't
bring a קרבן *korban*, so there's אם לא קרבנו *im lo korbano*.
So you can only bring your קרבן *korban* ולא גזול *velo gozul*.
So אימת *eimat*? When are we talking about? אילימא לפני ייאוש *eileima
lifnei yeiush*? פשיטא *pshita*! למה לי קרא *lama li kra*? So of
course if it's before ייאוש *yeiush*, you know,
I can't bring it, that's for sure. I don't need a פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* to tell me that I can't bring it. אלא לאחר
ייאוש *ela l'achar yeiush*. ושמע מינה ייאוש לא קני *ushma mina yeiush
lo kani*. שמע מינה *shma mina*. And I can learn from here
that ייאוש *yeiush* doesn't work either because that's what the פסוק pasuk.
*pasuk* is telling you. If it's גזול *gozul*, I don't care whether
it's ייאוש *yeiush* or not, you cannot bring it. But wait a
minute, if you remember how we started the day, we learned by
רבא *Rava* saying like oh, we had this exact same thing and
רבא *Rava* asked on him, oh what are you going to do
about משכא *mishka*? גזול ולא גזול *gozul velo gozul*? Nah, you know,
also he said it's the whole case was different. That it wasn't
that I stole your חולין *chulin* animal and made it into a
קרבן *korban*, rather I stole your קרבן *korban* animal, right? So so
why so how are you learning from here
that it doesn't make a difference if it's ייאוש *yeiush* and we're
talking about you stole the חולין *chulin*? You're the one that said
before רבא דאמר גזל קרבן חברו *Rava d'amar gazal korban chaveiro*. So
you know you gave a different answer before. Well now what are
you what are you giving this answer here now for? So שינוייא
סמי מכאן *shinuyei smi mikan*? או o, שינוייא אחרינא הוא *o shinuyei
achrina hu*? רב פפא אמר *Rav Papa amar*. All right, so he
changed his mind and now he's trying to say that ייאוש *yeiush*
makes no difference, right? Whereas before he was trying to answer רבא
*Rava* says ייאוש *yeiush* does make a difference, right? So you know
that was our problem. So so he changed his mind, you know,
he's giving this different answer or, you know, no, רבא *Rava* didn't
change his mind and, you know, and you're seeing רבא *Rava* giving
different opinions, one of them is רב פפא *Rav
Papa*. So anyway now we're seeing now at least from these past
two teachings we've seen that ייאוש *yeiush* does not have an effect.
That's exactly what we're trying to prove over here.
So one second.
I'm sure someone talks about this.
So I don't know what you do with this other case before.
I
guess I guess it was a case, I guess the case is
when it's קרבנו ולא גזול *korbano velo
gozul*. I have to think about it, I don't know, I'll have
to think about it.
It might depend on whether you stole it in its קרבן *korban*
state or its or in its חולין *chulin* state.
But then again, if it was before ייאוש *yeiush* then you know
then we're just saying that it's that it's so simple.
Or you could say that the מדרש *midrash* there maybe they're different
teachings, you
know, like we had a whole bunch of different תנאים *Tannaim* different
teachings one way or the other. So this so maybe one of
them is going down on one side of it.
But I don't know. Does the note say anything?
All right. Well let's go on.
I didn't think yeah, I wasn't sure if we'd get this far.
So מידת תשלומין ארבעה וחמישה arba'ah v'chamishah. *midas tashlumim arba v'chamisha* is
only by a שור shor *shor* and a שה seh, *seh*. That's
it, right? Doesn't apply to a חמור *chamor* let's say.
So I'll write down the פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* שמות *Shemot* twenty one.
Always better to do it from here.
All right.
Okay. Well
let me know if you see anything while I'm writing this פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* down so feel free to chime in.
All right. שמות *Shemot* twenty one.
There was awkward silence in the recorder but I'm writing it down.
All right.
Yeah, that was awkward silence in the
recorder,
but I'm ready to go. ילקוט שמעוני. I always like, if I
post it, I like getting the
spelling
right. Okay, that is our פסוק which is the basis for ארבעה
וחמישה. כי יגנב איש שור או
שה.
ki yignov ish
shor o seh. I really need another color. Let's see.
What other colors do we have?
Any?
Another color really makes all the difference. All dried out.
That's such a pity.
Oh well.
Let's see. Let's try these. Does this work?
Oh good. שור או שה. shor o seh.
And then שור או שה,
shor o
seh, right? So it says it twice. That's the פסוק. So again,
I'll read, I don't know if I've ever said the whole פסוק.
כי יגנב איש שור או שה. ki yignov ish shor o seh.
So you steal an ox or a sheep. וטבחו או מכרו, u'tvacho
o m'charo, so you, you know, butcher it or you sell it.
חמישה בקר ישלם, chamishah vakar yishalem, so you know, you pay in
kind, like you know, five cattle for the ישלם תחת השור, yishalem
tachat hashor, for the ox. וארבע צאן תחת השה, v'arba tzon tachat
hasheh, or you know, four for the sheep,
including the principal. Yeah, including the principal. So you have to pay
that too. So that's our basis for these פסוקים. pesukim. So the
question is, this is, is our משנה mishna stated restricted to just
a שור או שה? shor o seh? So the question is why?
למה אינלף שור שור משבת? lama inalaf shor shor mi'shabbat? מה להלן,
ma l'halan, you know, because it says in שבת shabbat as well
that your שור shor, needs the rest as well. למען ינוח שורך
וחמרך וינפש בן אמתך והגר. l'ma'an yanuach shorecha vachamorecha v'yinafesh ben amatcha
vehager.
So you know, these things need to rest. So and just like
שבת, shabbat, it's not just like oh, just my שור, shor, right?
So it's everything I own. I can't work my, you know, whatever
it is. I can't work my birds, you know, nothing. מה בשבת
מה להלן חייב באף כל כיוצא בהן אף כאן חייב באף כל
כיוצא בהן. ma b'shabbat ma l'halan chayav b'af kol kiyotzei vahen af
kan chayav b'af kol kiyotzei vahen. So why don't you, why are
we saying that שור או שה shor o seh is very specific
to שור או שה, shor o seh, right? Why don't we say
it means everything? I have to pay four or five. We'll work
it out, you know, what do you pay four for, what do
you pay five for? But you know, at least it's not just
the principal. So אמר רבא קרא שור ושה שור ושה שתי
פעמים שור ושה אין מידי אחרינא לא.
amar rava kra shor v'seh shor v'seh shtei pe'amim shor
v'seh in midi achrina lo. Because it says you know, שור או
שה shor o seh once, then חמישה בקר ישלם תחת השור וארבע
צאן תחת השה, chamishah vakar yishalem tachat hashor v'arba tzon tachat hasheh,
right? It says it twice. So that's twice. So it's being very
specific.
So meaning like, it didn't need to say it that way.
So now we're going to say, what do you mean it didn't
need to say it? What could it have said? You know, for
you to say that. His point is, oh, this is like, you
know, extra so to speak. And we do this all the time.
Like you know, you learn something that's extra that comes to teach
you this specific דין. din. So now we're going to say what's
extra, because it could have said it differently. How could it have
said it? And the גמרא's gemara going to go through a whole,
you know, back and forth as to what it could have said.
And then say, no, it couldn't have said that because then you
would have thought this. Oh, it could have said that because you
would have thought that. So meaning if, if this is the only
thing it could have said, right, then we can't learn that it's
just specific to שור או שה. shor o seh. No, it's saying
it because like that's how it has to be said that way.
And it's not anything particularly meaningful to say it this way. And
therefore we should learn from שבת shabbat and therefore it shouldn't just
be for שור או שה, shor o seh, right? So you're saying
because it says it twice, that's very, you know, important. So I'm
just going to tell you it's not that important, you know. So
now we're going to go through it.
Hopefully we'll get to the two dots.
So שור ושה, shor v'seh, okay, fine.
So האי מיותר אילימא שור ושה דסיפא, hai meyutar ileima shor v'seh
d'seifa, meaning like this last part,
right, over here?
Easier
to, to see it when it's on the board, opposed to trying
to, you know, think of it in your mind. But if it
would have said the end of it, because what could it have
said? וליכתוב רחמנא כי יגנוב שור או שה, v'lichtov rachmana ki yignov
shor o seh, meaning keep the first part the same. So כי
יגנוב איש שור או שה, ki yignov ish shor o seh, fine.
וטבחו או מכרו חמישה בקר ישלם תחתיו וארבע צאן תחתיו, u'tvacho o
m'charo chamishah vakar yishalem tachtav v'arba tzon tachtav, right? It says חמישה
בקר ישלם תחת השור וארבע צאן תחת השה. chamishah vakar yishalem tachat
hashor v'arba tzon tachat hasheh. It could have said תחתיו. tachtav. And
we would have known בקר vakar is for the בקר vakar case
of שור, shor
and צאן tzon is for the צאן tzon case of שה, seh
right? So why does he say again שור או שה? shor o
seh? It could have just said חמישה בקר ישלם תחתיו וארבע צאן
תחתיו chamishah vakar yishalem tachtav v'arba tzon tachtav instead of saying חמישה
בקר ישלם תחת השור וארבע צאן תחת השה. chamishah vakar yishalem tachat
hashor v'arba tzon tachat hasheh. Right? That's his question. So איצטריך רחמנא
הכא, itztarich rachmana hacha, הוי אמינא בישלומי תשעה לכל חד וחד. hava
amina bishlumey tish'a lechol chad vechad. You would have thought,
since תחתיו tachtav is the same one, right, same word תחתיו, tachtav,
right? שור shor is very specific and שה seh, is very specific.
If it just said תחתיו, tachtav, you would have thought, you know,
like very interesting thought, I have to pay nine. In other words,
I don't care whether I steal a שור shor, or a שה,
seh, I have to pay, if I steal a שור, shor I
pay five בקר bakar and four צאן, tzon, right? I steal a
שה, seh, I pay also five בקר bakar and four צאן. tzon.
I would pay nine, right, because תחתיו, tachtav, what's תחתיו tachtav going
on, right? תחתיו tachtav is going on what we just mentioned before,
שור shor or שה, seh. right? Get it? Okay. I would have
thought you have to pay nine.
What do you mean? אי נימא כתיב תחתיו, i nima ktiv tachtav,
תחתיו, tachtav, right? It says no, if it would have said חמישה
בקר ישלם תחתיו chamisha bakar yeshalem tachtav וארבע צאן תחתיו, ve'arba tzon
tachtav, right?
No, each תחתיו tachtav is going for the respective שור shor or
שה. seh.
And then, and therefore תחתיו מיותר? tachtav meyutar?
And then could have, you know, then no, it's not מיותר. meyutar.
הוא מיבעי ליה לדרשא אחרינא. hu mibai lei ledrasha acharina. דתניא, detanya,
הרי שגנב שור harei sheganav shor שווה מנה, shave mane, ישלם תחתיו
נגידין. yeshalem tachtav negidin. Like let's say I stole, okay, look,
we have to pay back four or five, but like you know
what kind of four or five? Maybe I'll give you like a
bad four or five. I stole this nice healthy ox, I'll give
you like you know,
weakling
oxen, oxen at death's door, you know? Maybe I can do that?
No, so it says תחתיו, tachtav, תחתיו, tachtav, you know, you really
gotta like give you back like the same kind of quality that
I stole.
So,
so basically the point is it's not, it's not מיותר, meyutar, because
I would have said if I would have done תחתיו, tachtav, then,
then I would have thought you have to pay nine. And what
about like this, no, you wouldn't have thought that. No,
that's from another דרשא. drasha. Like, you know, so meaning if we
just said תחתיו, tachtav, I would have figured it out. The fact
that it says תחתיו tachtav twice does not mean specific, because I
would have used that תחתיו tachtav for another purpose, to teach that
you need to pay back good ones. So I need to pay
back five healthy sheep and four healthy oxen, both, for, you know,
stealing either a שור shor or a שה. seh So I still
would have thought that. So therefore, it needs to say שור shor,
and שה seh, specifically, right?
So I wouldn't have thought that. Okay, so fine, so the end
of, so we need the end, right? Okay, fine, so let's try
from the beginning. Maybe you don't need the beginning. Which is very
odd, to not have the beginning of anything when because the beginning's
telling you what you're talking about. But the גמרא gemara somehow thinks
you could have not mentioned the beginning of the פסוק and you
would still figure out the same law. אלא שור ושה דרישא למה
לי? ela shor veseh deriesha lama li? דכתיב רחמנא, dechtiv rachmana, כי
יגנוב איש, ki yignov ish, it doesn't say what, but כי יגנוב
איש וטבחו או מכרו חמישה בקר ישלם תחת השור וארבע צאן תחת
השה. ki yignov ish utvacho o mecharo chamisha bakar yeshalem tachat hashor
ve'arba tzon tachat haseh. The end would make clear what it is,
right? I steal. So I have to pay four for the צאן
tzon and five
for the שור, shor right? So I could have just said that.
Why does it say שור או שה? shor o seh? So no,
אי כתב רחמנא הכא, i katav rachmana hacha, if I would have
just said that, הוי אמינא דגנב תרוייהו hava amina deganav tarveihu וטבח
להו, vetavach lehu, that I have to steal both a שור shor
and a שה, seh. right? If I just would have said כי
יגנוב איש וטבחו
או מכרו, ki yignov ish utvacho o mecharo, right, if I don't
have the או, o right, the או is very important, right? שור
או שה shor o seh means one or the other. So if
I just, then I have to pay
the five for the שור shor and four for the שה. seh.
Okay, but like, but I still would have to steal, you know,
both of them. Get it?
So okay, fine, so you know, I understand four for one and
five for the other, so I slaughtered one. You know, I pay
four or five depending on what I slaughtered. But this would not,
the thing wouldn't come into effect
if I steal a שור and a שה. What about stealing just
one or the other? I wouldn't know. What do you mean you
wouldn't
know?
וטבחו כתיב, utvacho ktiv, לחד. lechad. Fine, okay, but if, ואימא עד
דגנב תרוייהו ומזבין להו, ve'eima ad deganav tarveihu umazvin lehu, and you
know, so I still think I have to steal both. I'm not
getting out of this. I still think that I stole one of
them and
maybe I just
sell one? No, what, או מכרו כתיב. o mecharo ktiv. I only
sell one, לחד. lechad. Fine, but still, ואימא עד דגנב תרוייהו וטבח
חד ומזבין חד. ve'eima ad deganav tarveihu vetavach chad umazvin chad. Maybe
I'd still think that, you know, I have to steal two and,
you know, slaughter one and sell one. No, או מכרו, o mecharo,
you wouldn't have thought that. או מכרו כתיב, o mecharo ktiv, I
know that it applies to just one being sold or slaughtered. But
still, the גמרא gemara is getting every, you know, the גמרא gemara
is not asking, getting to the question the way I framed it.
That if I just would have said that, I don't know it
applies to just stealing one or the other. Right? You wouldn't have
thought that I have to slaughter both? You wouldn't have thought that
I have to sell both? You wouldn't have thought I have to
slaughter one
and sell one and keep the other? Because, you know, because everything
is this in the singular, right?
טבחו, tvacho, מכרו, mecharo, right? But if it doesn't say שור או
שה, shor o seh, I would think it would mean I have
to steal both, right? You haven't answered that question yet. ואימא אכתי
הוי אמינא עד דגנב תרוייהו וטבח חד מנייהו ve'eima achati hava amina
ad deganav tarveihu vetavach chad minaihu או מזבין חד מנייהו. o mazvin
chad minaihu. Fine. אלא שור
דסיפא ושה דסיפא.
ela shor
desifa veseh desifa. So okay, fine. So the point is
we can't say that both of these are extra. Now we can't
say both of these... So something is extra to teach you that
it's specific to שור ושה shor v'seh because if nothing was extra
then we should just say and abstract it from the rest to
a regular שבת Shabbat case that it would apply to all animals,
just like we can't work all animals, so too we can't steal
any animals, and you know, if I steal a chicken I'd have
to pay multiple times the value, whatever, again how you work that
out I don't know, how much, three I don't know, you know,
like something more than one. אלא שור דסיפא, Ela shor d'seifa, so
okay fine, but maybe one of these is extra, meaning maybe one
of these is extra and then one of these is extra, because
I could've said, and it's still sort of what we're saying, אלא
שור דסיפא ושור דרישא מיעטיה. ela shor d'seifa v'shor d'reisha miatei. דכתיב
רחמנא Dichtiv Rachmana כי יגנוב איש שור וטבחו ומכרו חמישה בקר ישלם
תחתיו וארבע צאן תחת
השה. ki yignov ish shor u'tivacho u'mechoro chamisha bakar yeshalem tachtav v'arba
tzon tachat haseh. I could've said that. I mean, it sounds very
weird, but I guess the גמרא Gemara somehow thinks that that would
have been sufficient. So then you know, the גמרא's Gemara saying that
that would have been perfectly fine to say, so I don't need
to have you know both שור ושה shor v'seh in the beginning
and both שור ושה shor v'seh in the end. The fact that
it does, שור דסיפא ושור דרישא למה לי שמע מינה שור ושה
אין מידי אחרינא לא. shor d'seifa v'shor d'reisha lama li shma mina
shor v'seh in midei achrina lo. So we learn from this that
it's just specifically for those two animals. Whether you buy that דרשה
drasha or not, I don't know, but you know, nevertheless, even if
you don't buy the דרשה, drasha, I mean it still seems that
the הלכה halacha makes sense, it's just for שור ושה, shor v'seh,
you know what I mean? You know, the question may not have
been the best question, but it's basically reaffirming what we kind of
always, at least I think, intuitively understood, that it's just for these
cases. Alright, that is the end of that. We're now at דף
עה, daf ayin hey, hopefully in good
shape for תשעה באב Tisha B'av in a week. שבת שלום. Shabbat
Shalom.
Thank you very much.